Some of the debates got really vigorous
when it came to applications
and what I would call limit cases or
kind of extreme cases. So, for example,
um let's imagine a hospital of the
future that is so automated that a
patient could walk in,
get diagnosed, prescribe medication,
and discharge without ever encountering
a person. Technically possible, okay? Uh
now, it sounds like kind of weird and
spooky and we wouldn't want that, but
what if um that level of automation and
uh efficiency allows you to place
50 of these hospitals in the developing
region.
In a you know, in a
indigent area, right? Uh versus oh, uh
we need to staff it with at least two
people. Okay, well,
you know, you then you can only do 10.
And uh we we had you know, diversions
and it really then forced us to think uh
for everybody regardless of position,
but what does that bother you? What what
is missing?
>> If I can just maybe start off and and
just to both of you, um what were the
conversations like these last two days?
>> I think very productive conversations.
So, our group about 15 people with very
diverse expertise and uh really everyone
authentically engaged
in trying to think where will the AI
take us and how we can make sure that it
takes us in the direction that helps
preserve or maybe even amplify human
dignity and the common good. So, very
much aligned with the
uh
exhortation that Pope Leo included in
his letter.
>> I'll just add um Michael referred to the
group and the the quality of the group.
It was very diverse. So, we had um um
an executive from a hospital system, um
executives from insurance companies, a
medical school professor, theologians,
ethicists for a Catholic hospital uh
trade association. So, it was quite
rich. It's about 13 people. What was
really striking uh is with that
experience taking uh Catholic social
teaching uh principles, principles from
the intellectual tradition like human
dignity and how does that apply
practically within these separate
contexts for these individuals to make
it real? And that was really powerful.
>> Can you Can you both share maybe briefly
like what separates Catholic healthcare
from like general health healthcare?
>> Maybe I'll just quickly respond and then
Michael, you can add um
uh
clearly um
uh a Catholic sort of sensibility versus
um a secular sensibility
does have this primacy on human dignity,
sanctity of life.
Um you know, it also acknowledges
suffering and um as a formative
experience.
So, the way that might translate then
into the application of AI is as things
get more mechanized, as AI gets more
powerful and supplants human
capabilities, how do you preserve
the human connection in that uh
healthcare sort of event or
or or activity
um especially not just now, but like
decades from now. And so, we wrestled
with how do you define that sort of
bright line boundary where human needs
to be involved, when computers and AI
and robots will be, you know, arguably
more effective.
>> Right. Um I'll quote one of our session
participants who said that purpose of
Catholic healthcare is to extend the
healing ministry of Jesus Christ.
Right. And I think that that's a a
really important context. And I think
another participant emphasized that the
in the Catholic social teaching and as
it pertains to health care, the
spiritual and the physical
are part that's who we are as humans and
you cannot separate it. Right? So, that
has important implications
for the use of AI. We cannot say just
put the spiritual aside and look what AI
will do for the physical. We have to
keep the holistic context in mind,
right? And that's kind of underpins
human dignity. So, but that that's
that's the mission and the difference of
Catholic health care.
>> Where did you guys find the most
spirited debate?
>> I think an interesting question we were
trying to to address and I that Louis
comment cuz he
really
was going deep into it. The question was
the role of humans, people,
in the context of the health care
enterprise, right? So, the the very
interesting discussion was
how much can we delegate to artificial
intelligence and what are the tasks that
remain intrinsically human that you need
you need a person, right? Full
recognition, AI is not a person. So,
that's important to set aside very very
clearly, right? So, you need human
beings interacting with human beings in
the context of health care. But I think
where some differing views came is how
far we can allow artificial intelligence
to go versus where the human person
human being comes in.
>> Yeah, just
to what Michael was saying, the some of
the debates got really vigorous when it
came to applications
and what I would call limit cases or
kind of extreme cases. So, for example,
Um, imagine a hospital of the future
that is so automated that a patient
could walk in,
get diagnosed, prescribe medication,
and discharge without ever encountering
a person. Technically possible. Okay?
Uh, now, it sounds like kind of weird
and spooky and we wouldn't want that.
But, what if um, that level of
automation and
uh, efficiency allows you to place
50 of these hospitals in the developing
region.
In a, you know, in a in a
indigent area, right? Uh, versus, oh,
uh, we need to staff it with at least
two people. Okay, well,
you know, you then you can only do 10.
And uh, we we had, you know, divergences
and it really then forced us to think
uh, for everybody, regardless of
position, but what does that bother you?
What what is missing?
And that led to then a list
um, that was generated.
Well, you know, some people said, well,
what's missing is um,
uh, human accompaniment,
uh, a divine mediation,
um,
relationality.
Some people said, you know, we can't
really trust
uh, AI to be
uh,
without any human verification or
consent. So, there's a long list, but
that was where we had uh, some fierce
debates and and it's sort of
not surprising because uh, you know, you
can have a list of principles, it's
called principalism, but when you get to
the actual application, that's where
things get quite difficult.
>> When you when you both look at health
care and you know, applications for AI,
where is it actively, you know, helping
>> Right, so we spent a little bit of time
looking at the kind of three goals that
many health systems have. One is to
increase access to care. Access is a
major issue. Developed world, developing
world, there is an issue of access.
Affordability.
Health care in many countries like the
US is too expensive. People cannot
afford it.
And then reliability,
right? Receiving high-quality care
that's good and safe in this in this
context, right? So, those are those are
the goals. And then we can object to
pose the Catholic social teaching
principles and looked at examples of
applications of AI that would satisfy
one or more of these goals. So, to to
give an example, ambient scribes are
getting very popular, right? So, when
you come to the doctor when I take my
child to the pediatrician, it used to be
that the poor doctor had to type in and
talk to me or my child, right?
Multitasking.
Now, there is the ambient scribe that
listens to the conversation and creates
the clinical note that the doctor will
review afterwards, but it frees
the clinician to have a face-to-face
direct conversation. I like this example
because it shows how AI is
rehumanizing
the interaction in the health care
setting. Now, you also have to be
careful that the clinician reads the
note afterwards, right? That there are
there are not errors, but that's just
one example of positive application. And
in general general, there was consensus
in our group that back office tasks, the
tasks that do not that either enhance or
not affecting the patient-clinician
interaction, having them
delegated to AI, that's a positive,
right? Filling out forms, all the things
that we have nurses do or or other
health care professionals that have to
do with the operation of health care,
but not the encounter, I think AI can be
very helpful and that's viewed as a
positive.
>> What lines do you guys see clearly the
church should take to make sure that we
don't cross that line in terms of AI,
you know, replacing that human care?
>> Uh an example
uh was what we termed non-impersonation.
So, even if AI an AI entity could feel
like a person,
um it should be very clear to the
patient uh it is not a person. Like a
red light on a video recording. Um
um that was one example of a kind of a
bright line.
Um
um
another um you know, let's go back to
this personless hospital example. People
acknowledge, you know, you may want to
it may be the expedient thing to do,
proper thing to do,
but at a minimum, as an example, uh we
should provide everybody an option to
talk to and meet a real person in all of
these settings. Uh
So, those are two kind of examples of
sort of edge cases and and where, you
know, Catholic
uh
sensibilities, you know, uh come into
play. Can I just add one thing about the
question about um
um just the role of AI. I think um
you know, for people not in health care
systems, they should
uh it it uh
be aware this is pretty natural to think
of AI
and its concerns and a patient uh
clinician interaction. But, of course,
AI is suffused
everywhere. Uh administrative tasks,
um
uh
data
uh storage. Uh it's just not only the
patient uh
that uh doctor interaction. Uh
obviously, diagnosis, development of
drugs, it's everywhere. Uh we uh handed
out a sheet uh probably 50 areas where
AI is suffused uh in health care and for
most people it's not visible to them.
>> What are you both most excited about in
terms of the future?
>> So, I think there
is a lot of inefficiency
in healthcare, right? The costs are
rising, the quality as measured as life
expectancy and health is not going up.
So, right, there are issues of national
debt related to the cost of healthcare.
So, I think AI can be very helpful. I
mentioned the back office um
interactions, making it more efficient,
again, aligned with the good of
patients, right? So, I think there is we
can believe that we might be able to
improve care,
increase access, and reduce cost with
the use of technology.
I will say I think the next frontier is
more direct clinical applications. And
interestingly, um pre-pandemic, pre-GPT,
you saw a lot of development focused on
the clinical, better diagnosis, better
prediction, right? Going into the uh
preventing disease or or or curing
disease.
Post-pandemic with the strain on
healthcare and emergence of GPT
generative AI, which lends itself to the
more operational tasks, it shifted more
to the back office operations, and
that's where the focus is. But I hope
that
down the line we'll move into
the diagnosis, right? Being able to
catch breast cancer that's not visible
on mammography because AI is able to use
it, right? Those are the the examples
that will be through prevention will be
saving lives, identifying new treatments
and medicines, new cures that will come
in as a result of having AI. So, I think
it's It's process, but with tremendous
positive potential.
>> Um instead of answering what am I
excited about, since I'm not a a formal
practitioner, I'll I'll
address what I'm curious about with AI
in healthcare. And my personal focus is
and now that I'm transitioning from the
tech industry into the healthcare field,
it's in the area of hospice and
palliative care, end of care, end of
life care. And in and specifically, I'm
curious about
spiritual health.
Um
Uh I'm one of several
advisors to a physician George
Washington
University who Dr. Christina Christina
Puchalski
who leads an initiative to inculcate
more spiritual care
in clinics and hospitals. Essentially
raising the chaplain at a peer level
with doctors. And she has a lot of
research and and methods to measure
spiritual distress, to inculcate more
spiritual health.
What is a role in AI in that? Could AI
through this ambient listening
listen to a conversation, detect or in
advance, spiritual distress?
Um
And a controversial area is in
facilities where
there aren't enough nurses or chaplains.
Whether we like it or not, there are
already bots
that even little robots that that
provide some
facsimile of a companion in and what are
the issues with that? So those are the
things that I'm I'd say curious about.
>> I have one final question here.
If you had one thing you wanted the
institutional church or the or the
Vatican to to take seriously with
regards to healthcare and AI, what would
you want to see happen?
>> So recently I
have studied Rerum Novarum,
right encyclical written at the time of
a technological revolution from over 100
years ago, and it was very, very
influential, right? And we can see the
history meander through different
places, but the
spirit of Rerum Novarum helped shape it
and and and help kind of avoid the
extremes of communism on the one hand
and
uh unencumbered capitalism on the other.
And we're not in a perfect society, but
there is some kind of middle ground
here, right? So, I'm thinking that there
is an opportunity and but hopefully
you're choosing the name Leo, I think
pointing out in that direction.
I think uh the
society at large, as one of the
participants commented, this is the
opportunity for Catholic Church to lead.
There is a void in the ethical space,
right? So, having a well-thought-out
encyclical
on AI, and again, it's developing and
it's it's changing, right? It's not an
easy document to be writing, I think
would be would be very, very valuable
for Catholics, but I think for the world
at large.
>> I would add um
technical literacy that's
quite deep and acknowledges I think um a
lot of concerns around AI, even just
positive statements about AI,
uh is really um
addressing chatbots. Uh
When you really kind of dig down like
what do what what you know, what's your
vision of AI, your concerns, and what
what what are you envisioning? They're
really talking about chatbots. Um and AI
is much broader than that and it in 5,
10 years from now it'll be you know,
even broader than that. So, without that
kind of deep level of technical literacy
um that understands how AI works in
different domains,
um things stay at kind of a platitudinal
level and that would be unfortunate. Um
you know, we have Vatican scientists and
bioethics and even astronomy. Uh,
we need to demonstrate a similar level
of literacy for AI. The second thing I
would add is
is go below the principles and have case
studies and um, investigations when
these principles are actually applied in
really tough limit conditions. As you go
through you know, the different
Catholic social teaching principles,
some of them will force decisions that
are at odds with each other and odds at
each other and having case studies and
helping people discern that
is really important.
>> Well, Louis, Michael, this has been
wonderful. Thank you so much for the
time for the conversations and the
incredible work that you guys are doing.
I hope we can do this again at next
year's Builders AI Forum. Thanks for the
great questions.
>> Thank you for having us.